Guide to the Robert Edward Dawson papers, 1900-2008 RL.00294
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Organizations and Institutions, 1940-1999; undated
  - North Carolina Department of Social Services: Medicaid Advisory Committee, 1970-1975 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Hospital Association Newspaper, 1979 (Box 25)
  - North Carolina Medical Society, 1981-1983 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Medical Society, 1988-1994 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Society of Ophthalmology, Inc., 1981 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 1971-1978 (Box 13)
  - North Carolina Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 1978 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina Society for the Prevention of Blindness: Board of Directors, 1976-1978 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina Society to Prevent Blindness, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina Society to Prevent Blindness, 1981-1985 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina Society to Prevent Blindness, 1981-1990 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina Society to Prevent Blindness: Board of Directors, 1978-1985 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina State Education Assistance Authority, 1994 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society, 1976-1977 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society, 1980-1995 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society, 1983-1988 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society: 80th Annual Convention, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society: Budget Committee, 1981-1988 (Box 14)
  - Old North State Medical Society: Dr. Debnam--Alex--Watts Greene, etc., 1976-1982 (Box 14)
  - Positive Futures, Inc., Black College Policy Conference Packet, 1979 (Box 25)
  - President's Committee on the Employment of the Handicapped, 1972-1976 (Box 14)
  - St. Joseph's AME Church, 1981-1988 (Box 14)
  - Sigma Pi Phi Fraternity, 1971-1995 (Box 14)
  - Sigma Pi Phi Fraternity, 1979-1995 (Box 14)
  - Sigma Pi Phi Fraternity: Grand Baule, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
  - Sleep Disorders Center, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
  - Toastmasters International Youth Leadership Program, 1967-1968 (Box 14)
  - University Club, 1987 (Box 14)
  - University of North Carolina: Board of Governors Medical Scholarships, 1993-1996 (Box 14)
  - University of North Carolina: Board of Trustees, 1980-1990 (Box 14)
  - Watts School of Nursing Brochure, 1985-1986 (Box 14)
- Professional, 1939-2002; undated
  Includes Dawson's files regarding his medical practice, speeches, lectures, writings, meetings and conferences. Subject matter in the letters primarily focuses on medical practice matters.
  - Addresses, Misc. Organizations, 1974-1980 (Box 15)
  - American Academy of Ophthalmology, Focus Points, 1984 (Box 15)
  - ASOA American Society of Cataract and Refractive Surgery, 1990 (Box 15)
  - Associated Health Services, Inc., 1993-1994 (Box 15)
  - Association of Eye Care Centers, Inc., 1988 (Box 15)
  - Audiocassette: Unlabeled, undated (Box 26, Audio-cassette RL00294-MCS-0001)
  - Audiocassette: Unlabeled, undated (Box 26, Audio-cassette RL00294-MCS-0002)
  - Audiocassette: MMC Barrett P.M., 1981 (Box 26, Audio-cassette RL00294-MCS-0003)
  - Audiocassette: No. 1 Task Force, undated (Box 26, Audio-cassette RL00294-MCS-0004)
  - Audiocassette: MMC Slash{?], undated (Box 26, Audio-cassette RL00294-MCS-0005)
  - Black Leadership, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Black Man, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Continuing Medical Education, 1974-1995; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 15)
  - Cost/Health Care, 1992 (Box 15)
  - Department of Human Resources [U.S.], 1989 (Box 15)
  - Diabetic Retinopathy Study, 1974 (Box 15)
  - Diseases, Glaucoma, 1985-1991 (Box 15)
  - Drug Therapy Reactions, 1992 (Box 15)
  - Durham Ambulatory Services, 1983-1985 (Box 15)
  - Durham Ambulatory Surgical Center, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
  - EDS Standing Committee of Physician Consultants, 1981-1983 (Box 15)
  - Eye Therapy, 1980-1981 (Box 15)
  - Eyes (Glass), 1963 (Box 15)
  - Frame Price List, 1992 (Box 15)
  - Glaucoma, 1965-1982 (Box 15)
  - Lectures, 1966-1970 (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1964-1996 (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1970-1971 (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1973 (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1974; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Letters, 1976; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Letters, Jan-June, 1977 (Box 15)
  - Letters, July-Dec., 1977; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Letters, 1978; 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Letters, 1979-1981 (Box 16)
  - Letters, 1984-1997 (Box 16)
  - Letters, 1989-1991 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Filed A-M, 1981 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Filed A-N, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Filed N-Z, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Filed A-N, 1983 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Filed A-N, 1983 (Box 25)
  - Letters, Pick Up Glasses, 1978-1987 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Typed A-M, 1981 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Typed A-N, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Typed N-Z, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Letters and Photographs, 1939-1981; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Maxi care, 1988-1989 (Box 17)
  - Medicaid, 1961-1995 (Box 17)
  - Medical Associates, Inc., 1957-1970 (Box 17)
  - Medical Review of N.C., 1989-1992 (Box 17)
  - Medical Surgical Nursing Course, 1968 (Box 17)
  - Meetings and Conferences, 1967-1993 (Box 17)
  - Minorities in Medicine Publications, 1983-1995 (Box 17)
  - Muscle Balance, 1970 (Box 17)
  - N.C. Chapter of the American College of Surgeons, 1969-1973 (Box 17)
  - News Items of Interest, 1979-1999 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina College Health Service, 1959-1969 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Department of Human Resources: Division for the Blind, 1988-1995 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Department of Human Resources: Division of Medical Assistance, 1982-1993 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Department of Human Resources: Division of Social Services, 1973-1979 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Division of Social Services, Medicaid, Title XX, 1974 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Eye and Human Tissue Bank, 1967-1984 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Joint Council of Health Education, 1962-1964 (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Medical Assistance Program Handbook, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Ocular Bacteriology, undated (Box 17)
  - Office Manager, 1976-1984; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Ophthalmology, 1980-1985 (Box 17)
  - Papers, 1964-1980 (Box 17)
  - Portrait, 2000 (Box 17)
  - Public Interest, 1979-1990 (Box 17)
  - Publications, 1978-1989 (Box 17)
  - Quiglass, Milton, Jr., M.D., 1978-1988 (Box 18)
  - Return to Dawson, 1966-1980 (Box 18)
  - Setting Up a Medical Corporation, 1973-1974 (Box 18)
  - Student National Medical Association Sickle Cell Disease Proposal, undated (Box 18)
  - Speech: Address to House of Delegates, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Bedside Manner of a Computer, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: California Regional Address, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Drafts, National Medical Association, 1989 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Farewell Address, National Medical Association, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Fed. Impact on Med. Manpower, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: First House of Delegates Address, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Hinson Award to General Guthrie, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Jackson, Miss., and Gary, Indiana, 1979-1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Lawyers, Nurses, Doctors, Dentists, Pharmacy, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Material, 1976-1980; 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Speech: Meharry Commencement Address, 1980; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Speech: Meharry Commencement Anatomy of Speech, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: National Medical Association Inaugural Address, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: President's Report to House of Delegates, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Regional Meeting, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: St. Louis Union Mem. United Methodist Church, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: Song of the Nightingale, Commencement Address NCCU Nursing, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speech: South Carolina, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speech: United Methodist Church St. Louis, Mo., undated (Box 18)
  - Speeches, 1979-2002 (Box 18)
  - Speeches/editorials, 1979 (Box 18)
  - Speeches: Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Speeches: Other, 1979-1989 (Box 18)
  - Tom Gilmore, Deputy Secretary, N.C. Department of Human Resources, 1979-1980 (Box 18)
  - Writing Drafts, 1995; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Writings, 1957-1999 (Box 18)
  - Loose Material, 1954-2000; undated; 23 folders (Box 19)
    Includes material that was never filed. Some items belong in the Organizations and Institutions Series, including meeting agenda and packets, along with some incoming professional letters. However, the files primarily include clippings, brochures, handouts, direct mailings, newsletters, programs, bulletins, magazines, and other materials related to ophthalmology and Dawson's personal or professional interests. There are also a few of Dawson's draft letters and speeches.
  - Loose Material, 1954-2000; undated; 16 folders (Box 20)
- Personal, 1880-2008
  Includes Dawson's personal files, especially regarding his military career, memorabilia, the Lawson Street project (plans for building his house), and retirement. There are black-and-white and color photographs and negatives, along with one tintype, primarily reflecting Dawson's family life.
  - Address book, 1992 (Box 21)
  - Biographical Information, 1983-1996 (Box 21)
  - Budget, 1954 (Box 21)
  - Building Trades Blueprint Reading [manual], 1994 (Box 21)
  - Calendar and Financial Sheets, 1978; undated (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Church Programs, 1994-1997 (Box 21)
  - Datebook, 1991 (Box 21)
  - Durham Academy School, 1967-1969 (Box 21)
  - Ellerby, Ron L., 1983-1987 (Box 21)
  - I Dream a World (book), 1989 (Box 25)
  - Janice Dawson, 1971-1993 (Box 21)
  - Julia Dawson, 1987-1989 (Box 21)
  - Lawson Street Construction, 1958-1984 (Box 21)
  - Memorabilia, 1936-1985; 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Military Estate and Benefits, 1954-1956 (Box 21)
  - Military Records, 1954-1987 (Box 21)
  - Poster (unidentified person), undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Retirement, 1974-1997 (Box 21)
  - Scrapbook, 1969-1981 (Box 21)
  - Who's Who, 1980-1982 (Box 21)
  - Window Man (Lawson Street Project), 1988-1989 (Box 21)
  - Book: Memories of the Southern Civil Rights Movement by Danny Lyon, 1992 (Box 21)
  - Yearbook: A and T College of North Carolina, 1966 (Box 21)
  - Photographs: Unlabeled, staff(?) at Dr. Dawson's practice, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Unidentified Group Photo, Class Photo?, 1980-1989 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, City of Medicine Awards, 2002 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Includes Christmas 1990s; Georgia, 1996, Allison Walker, 1990s, Alpha Phi Alpha, 1996, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs and Negatives: Unlabeled Snapshots, Wedding and New Baby, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Unlabeled Snapshots, Includes House Interiors and Exteriors, Wedding, Family, 1980-1999; 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Unlabeled, 1980-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Unlabeled, Christmas, Family, Reunion, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Unlabeled, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs, Negatives: Family Snapshots, 1980-2008 (Box 22)
  - Photographs, Negatives: Family Snapshots, Masons Meeting, 1990-2008 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Unidentified Church Ceremony, 1980-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Masons, Travel, Family, 1990-2008 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Family Snapshots of Melanie's Wedding Celebration, 1980-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Family Snapshots, Guardsmen, Family Reunion, Disney World/ Sea World, Post-wedding Party, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Swearing-in Ceremony, Dinner, 1995 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Negatives, Unidentified, 1990-2008 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Negatives, Unidentified, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Robert at Commencement of Meharry Medical College (50 Year Reunion), 1993 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Album (Family Snapshots), 1970-1979; 3 folders (Box 22)
  - [Photographs Removed from White Folder], Travel, Family, 1950-1989 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Family Snapshots, Biltmore, Grove Park Inn, 1996 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Family Snapshots, Panoramics, 1990-1999 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Unidentified Family, 1990-2008 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Family Snapshots, Unidentified--Loose, 1990-2008 (Box 22)
  - Photographs: Unidentified Family Snapshots, 1990-1999 (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Unidentified Family Snapshots, 1980-1999 (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Snapshots, Unidentified, Loose, Family, 1990-1999 (Box 23)
  - Photographs: Family Portraits, Including One Tintype, 1880-1989 (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Unidentified, Family and Friends, Graduation, Event, Photocopies, Negatives, 1990-1999 (Box 24)
  - Photographs: Slides, Unidentified Travel, Event, Hospital Employee, 1980-1989 (Box 24)